[MUSIC]
[음악]
Okay, well we've talked quite exhaustively about this notion of clustering for
문서 검색에서의 클러스터링이란 무엇인가에 대해
the sake of doing document retrieval, but there are lots,
철저하게 알아봤습니다
and lots of other examples where clustering is useful, and
사실 클러스터링이 유용한 분야는 수도 없이 많은데
I wanna take some time just to describe a few of them.
그중 몇 개를 설명드리고자 합니다
So one application is for image search.
그중 한 응용 분야는 이미지 검색입니다
So imagine you're going and you're searching,
구글 이미지 검색에 가서
you go on Google Image search and you type in the word ocean.
바다란 단어를 입력했다고 하죠
Well it would be really helpful if we could structure all the images we have by
그럴 경우 미리 모든 이미지를
some set of categories like ocean, pink flower, dog, sunset, clouds.
바다, 핑크색 꽃, 개, 노을, 구름 등의 카테고리별로 구성해놓는 게 무척 유리하겠죠
So clustering is very helpful for doing structured search.
그러므로 클러스터링은 구조적 검색에 아주 요긴합니다
Another very different application is maybe we wanna group patients by
다른 응용으로는 환자를 건강 상태에 따라
their medical condition.
나누는 것을 생각할 수 있습니다
So here a goal might be to better
목표는 여러 질병과 함께 모집단의 특징을
characterize subpopulations as well as different diseases.
잘 나타내는 것입니다
So as an example, we can look at a whole bunch of patients that have seizures.
예를 들어 발작 환자가 아주 많이 있다고 하죠
So these three brains represent three different patients, and
세 환자의 뇌인데 발작 활동을
they have different recording setups that are measuring their seizure activity.
측정하는 기록 설정이 서로 다릅니다
And so for each of these patients we get a collection of recordings
장시간에 걸쳐 각 환자가 겪는 여러 종류의
of different seizures that they exhibit over time.
발작 기록이 주어집니다
So each one of these colored squares represents
색칠된 사각형은
a different recording of a seizure.
발작 기록을 나타냅니다
And between these different patients there might be
환자 사이에 비슷한 유형의 발작이
similar types of seizures that appear in these different patients.
존재할지도 모릅니다
And so what we can do is we can take all of these seizure recordings from these
세 환자의 발작 기록을 전부 모아
three different patients and think about clustering them.
클러스터링해봅니다
And if we identify different types of seizures in this way,
각 유형의 발작을 이렇게 판별한다면
this can allow us to better treat the types of patient that
발작 유형에 대한 이해를 바탕으로
we're observing based on understanding what types seizures they exhibit.
치료 기술의 향상이 가능해집니다
Well another application is thinking about doing product recommendation on Amazon.
다른 응용으로 아마존의 상품 추천도 들 수 있죠
So, for example, on Amazon there are a lot of third parties that come and
예를 들어 아마존에는 수많은 공급업체가
they post some product to be sold.
상품을 올립니다
And they provide a label of what that product is.
상품 라벨도 붙이죠
So, for example, maybe a person wants to sell a crib and
유아용 침대를 팔고 싶은 사람은
they label the crib, fairly reasonably, as being a furniture item.
합리적인 가구 라벨을 붙입니다
So maybe we get posted under the furniture category.
그러면 가구 카테고리에 나타나게 되겠죠
But, if instead, we look at who purchases this item?
하지만 구매자 목록을 보면 어떨까요?
And we look at their purchase history, and
구매 이력을 살펴보니
we look at other people with similar purchase histories, so
비슷한 이력을 가진 다른 사람들이
maybe the person who purchased this item also purchased baby car seat, well
유아용 카시트도 구입했다고 하면
then maybe what we can do is maybe we can infer that a better label for this crib,
유아용 침대에 대해서도 가구가 아니라
which had been labeled furniture is really to have labeled it as a baby product.
유아용품이란 라벨을 붙이는 게 더 나을지 모릅니다
So in addition to discovering groups of products that are related, that have.
이렇게 관련 상품 그룹 발견 외에도
Based on purchase histories of these items we can also
품목의 구매 이력을 바탕으로
use that to discover groups of related users on Amazon.
관련 사용자 그룹을 발견할 수 있습니다
And that can be used for targeting products to those users.
이렇게 사용자 대상 상품추천에 활용할 수 있습니다
And finally we can think about structuring web search results.
마지막으로 웹 검색 결과 구조화를 떠올려 봅시다
So, for example,
그러면, 예를 들어,
search terms can have multiple meanings like the word "cardinal".
검색 단어는 눈처럼 여러 의미를 가질 수 있습니다 (원문은 cardinal)
If I type this in to Google, maybe I mean I want an article about a cardinal,
눈을 구글에 입력하면 하늘에서 내리는 눈,
the bird, maybe about the baseball team, or about a cardinal, a religious figure.
사람이나 동물의 눈을 의미할 수도 있죠
So if we can structure out articles based on their content,
이 모듈에서 알아본 바와 같이
using the same types of ideas we've talked about in this module,
내용에 따라 기사를 구조화하면
then I can improve my search results that I provide to people.
검색 결과를 향상시킬 수 있습니다
And the list of applications goes on and on.
응용 분야는 이 외에도 많습니다
Another one that's quite interesting is thinking about
또 하나 흥미로운 주제는
collections of neighborhoods and
여러 지역이 있을 때
there are a few applications where you want to discover similar neighborhoods.
비슷한 지역을 판별하는 게 유용할 때가 꽤 있습니다
One is if we wanna estimate the price of a house at a very small local
그중 하나는 아주 좁은 지역의
regional level.
주택 가격을 추정하는 것이지요
So in this case, it challenges the fact that we only have a few, or
이 경우 좁은 지역이라면
very often, no house sale observations within a very small neighborhood.
샘플이 없거나 아주 적다는 게 난제입니다
So if we wanna estimate the value of the house in that neighborhood
추정의 기반으로 삼을 주택이 없기 때문에
at a point in time, it's very hard to do that
특정 시점에서 주택 가격을
because we have no other houses to base our estimate off of in that neighborhood.
추정하기가 매우 어렵습니다
However, if we can discover other neighborhoods that have
하지만 주택 유형, 가격 움직임이 비슷한
similar types of house dynamics, house price dynamics, then
지역을 찾는다면
we can come up with a good estimate of the house in the neighborhood with few or
그 지역의 정보를 활용해
no sales by leveraging information from this other neighborhood
데이터가 없는 지역의 주택 가격 추정도
that was discovered to be related to the current neighborhood.
가능해집니다
So, the idea is to discover clusters of neighborhoods, and
지역들의 클러스터를 발견하고
then within those clusters we can share information like these house sales
클러스터 간의 주택 판매 등의 정보 공유를 통해
informations to form better estimates.
추정을 개선합니다
So, this is the solution that I'm describing here, is to cluster regions
제가 설명드리는 방법은 유사한 경향의
with similar trends, and then share information within a cluster.
지역을 클러스터링하고 클러스터 내부의 정보를 공유합니다
And the same idea of discovering related regions can be used for helping
관련 지역 발견이란 개념은 강력 범죄 예측을 통해
to forecast violent crimes, to better task police forces to different regions.
경찰력 배치 계획 수립에도 도움을 줄 수 있습니다
So again once we discover different neighborhoods that have very
유사한 범죄 동향을 가진 여러 지역들을 찾아
similar crime dynamics, we can form better predictions of the rates
강력 범죄율 예측을 개선하고
of violent crimes in those neighborhoods and
이 정보를 통해
then use that information to task police to those regions.
경찰력을 적절히 배치합니다
[MUSIC]
[음악]